Guide to the Papers of Cecilia Razovsky (1886-1968), undated, 1913-1971
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, N.Y.
Papers of Cecilia Razovsky
undated, 1913-1971
Cecilia Razovsky
The papers consist of correspondence and reports of Cecelia Razovsky (married name: Davidson), noted social worker specializing in immigration and resettlement of refugees. The collection includes information about her work with the National Council of Jewish Women in the 1920's, and with the National Refugee Service (and predecessor organizations) in the 1930's. Information is included about her work as a Resettlement Supervisor in the post-World War II Displaced Persons camps in Europe, and as a field worker in the southwestern U.S. for the United Service for New Americans in 1950. The collection contains reports and correspondence from her trips to South America, primarily Brazil: to explore possibilities of refugee settlement in 1937 and 1946; as a representative for United HIAS Service to aid in settling Egyptian and Hungarian refugees in 1957-1958; and as a pleasure trip and evaluation of the changes in the Jewish community of the country in 1963. Also included in the collection are many of Razovsky's articles, plays, and pamphlets.
3 linear feet + 1 Oversized folder
*P-290
American Jewish Historical Society at the Center for Jewish History
Razovsky, Cecilia
Cecilia Razovsky was an immigration and refugee relief worker whose extraordinary career spanned the early 1900s to the 1960s. Her life's work began with assisting Eastern European immigrants in the early 1900's, continued with helping German refugees during World War II, working overseas in Displaced Persons Camps, aiding refugees in United States Detention Camps after the War, encouraging Jewish communities in Southwest United States to take refugee families, and culminated with organizing resettlement efforts in South America, Central America, and the West Indies. She worked for major refugee relief organizations: National Council of Jewish Women, National Refugee Service, German Jewish Children's Aid, United Service for New Americans, Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society Service, and the Citizen's Committee on Displaced Persons. Against resistant administrations, she tirelessly negotiated for admissions of German children into the United States, landing rights for the SS. St. Louis in Cuba and the SS Quanza in Mexico and the United States, and increasing immigration opportunities in the Americas and West Indies.
Born May 4, 1886 to immigrant parents Minna and Jonas Razovsky in St. Louis, MO, Razovsky sewed buttons on overalls in a factory at age 12 to contribute to her family's income. She held a variety of jobs after school, working as a salesgirl, waitress, laundress, stenographer, clerk, and secretary until she took up teaching for the Jewish Educational Alliance in St. Louis at age 18. There, she gave evening lessons in English and History to immigrants and taught Biblical literature and Hebrew to children on Saturdays and Sundays. In 1911, she became an Attendance Officer for the St. Louis Board of Education, interviewing applicants and issuing employment certificates to children who qualified under the new Child Labor Law. She oversaw the probation of delinquent girls and studied the street trade situation in St. Louis in 1912. This position led her in 1917 to become an Inspector for the Child Labor Division, Children's Bureau, in Washington, D.C. She inspected mills and factories in Alabama, Eastern Ohio, and Virginia for compliance to the Child Labor Law. She examined the physical and educational development of Southern children, studied the effect of the First World War on child labor and school attendance throughout the United States, and surveyed the administration of the Child Labor Law in the District of Columbia. Concurrently, she attended classes in social work, drama, literature, economics, law, psychology, labor problems, public relations, and Spanish in a variety of schools in St. Louis, Chicago, and New York. 1 In 1918, the Supreme Court declared federal child labor laws to be unconstitutional (child labor reforms were established in the late 1930s ), and the Child Labor Division ceased. 2
National Council of Jewish Women, 1921-1934
Razovsky returned to her earlier inclination towards helping immigrants and in 1921 became Executive Secretary for the National Council of Jewish Women's (NCJW) Department of Immigrant Aid. As she writes, "I was always interested in the literature about immigrants, living among them in my youth, and the stories in English written about them were to me fascinating and all the authors, like Anzia Yierska [Yezierska] Kahn, were my heroes and heroines..." 3
Her unusual abilities were noticed and a year later she was appointed Associate Director. She also served as Editor of the NCJW bulletin, The Immigrant, for ten years.
In 1921, President Harding signed the "Three Per Cent Immigration Law" and in 1924 a permanent Immigration Restriction Bill was put into effect. NCJW worked on legislation, oriented immigrants to their new life in the United States, and established a Bureau of International Case Work to help reunite immigrants with their families overseas. Razovsky traveled throughout the United States training local NCJW committees on how to organize English and Citizenship classes. She met immigrants arriving at Ellis Island and other ports and developed international services to relatives abroad through agencies in Europe, Asia, and South America. She lectured for students and professional groups, conducting Institutes on Education of the Foreign Born. In 1922, Razovsky authored her first book; What Every Emigrant Should Know. She wrote What Every Woman Should Know About Citizenship in 1926. This book addressed the Cable Act of 1922, which required women to apply individually for citizenship versus making them automatic citizens under their husband's name. Although feminists saw the Act as a victory, it increased the hardship of many immigrant women, who were in greater danger of being deported; deserted overseas; and denied pensions, medical care, and employment. In 1938, Razovsky updated What Every Woman Should Know About Citizenship with a booklet titled Making Americans. This booklet, directed at the volunteer community, gave instructions on how to set up naturalization committees and bureaus, and provided information on immigration law and procedures. 4
Razovsky was sent as a NCJW delegate to the First World Congress of Jewish Women in Austria in 1923 and addressed the conference on immigration. After the conference, she toured European ports and evaluated conditions for refugees. Many refugees prevented from entering the United States were admitted into Cuba and Razovsky was sent there in 1924 to assist and evaluate the poor conditions for emigrant Jews. Razovsky served, from 1925-1935, as Secretary of the Jewish Committee for Cuba. In 1931, Razovsky visited Russia in order to study social service conditions.
During this time, she was highly involved in legislation and policy making, attending major conferences and committees on immigration and particularly on the German refugee crisis during the 1930s. She served in various capacities for the National Conference of Social Work from 1926-1929, including as Chair of Division X in 1927 and Chair of Conference on Immigration Policy in 1928. In 1929, Razovsky represented several American organizations at the International Association for the Protection of Migrants, an advisory committee to the League of Nations in Geneva. Jane Addams appointed her in 1932 as a representative at the International Conference for Social Work in Frankfurt, Germany. The same year, she served as Chair for the National Council on Naturalization and Citizenship, studying increased naturalization fees. In 1933 she chaired an advisory committee on legislation reform for the Ellis Island Committee of Forty Eight that was appointed by Secretary of Labor Frances Perkins. She also served as a chair and secretary for the General Committee of Immigration Aid at Ellis Island and NY Harbor from 1933-1936. 5
In between Razovsky's whirlwind of activities, she married Dr. Morris Davidson in 1927. Dr. Davidson, a certified opthamologist, accompanied Razovsky on her later trips to South America, assisting her with her work, and became an expert in Brazilian culture and history. 6
National Coordinating Committee, 1934-1939
The pressure on the State Department to admit German refugees escaping the rise of Nazism in Germany did not waive restrictions on immigration quotas until late 1936, when a slight change in wording regarding public charges increased visa issuance but not to the extent needed to help the increasing wave of refugees. 7 It was clear a centralized refugee relief agency was needed to assist non-Jewish and Jewish German refugees, one more comprehensive than the current Joint Clearing Bureau which was under the American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee. The League of Nations appointed James G. McDonald as High Commissioner for Refugees in 1933. McDonald and Chairman Joseph P. Chamberlain, Professor of Public Law at Columbia University, established the National Coordinating Committee for Aid to Refugees and Emigrants Coming from Germany (NCC), a successor agency to the Joint Clearing Bureau. NCC's plans were based upon a report Razovsky wrote in January 1934 (Razovsky had also served as Secretary for the Joint Clearing Bureau ). NCJW loaned Razovsky to pioneer this new organization, and a small office opened with Razovsky as Executive Director in July 1934. The staff grew to 180 by February 1939 and in June 1939, NCC merged with two other organizations to form the National Refugee Service (NRS). Affiliated with NCC was the German Jewish Children's Aid, an organization headed by Razovsky to negotiate the admission and later placement of German Jewish refugee children. 8
The NCC began with approximately 20 non-Jewish and Jewish member organizations, serving as a national clearinghouse and registry. In addition, NCC dealt with affidavits, quotas, visas, and financial aid. The bureau helped refugees find employment throughout the United States and evaluated projects specifically designed for refugees with specific occupations. NCC educated the non-Jewish public on the refugee problem, urged local communities to help refugees resettle outside of New York City, and strengthened local committees to care for refugees throughout the United States. The agency cooperated with government agencies, worked with the League of Nations High Commissioner for Refugees Coming from Germany, and coordinated the work of existing relief organizations throughout the United States and abroad. 9
The NCC looked for escape avenues for refugees all over the globe. The prospects in Central and South America led Razovsky and her husband to visit São Paulo and Rio de Janeiro, Brazil and Buenos Aires, Argentina in 1937 in order to evaluate conditions and anti-Semitism for German refugees. In São Paulo, Razovsky met Dr. Ludwig and Luiza Lorch for the first time. Dr. Lorch headed a committee for German refugee relief and Mrs. Lorch was involved in the women's committee. They would become important friends to the Davidsons, aiding Razovsky in many areas of social work in São Paulo, Brazil. 10
In November 1938, after Kristallnacht, Razovsky described the "tense and feverish" atmosphere in her office; they received 1300 callers each day. Restricted viciously by the quota of bringing 20 refugee children per month into the United States, Razovsky writes, "We not only are not taking large groups but we are even slowing up on those whom we have ordered under the auspices of the German-Jewish Children's Aid, because of the long delays in the quota... At the end of the day we are literally in rags-physically and mentally..." 11
On June 2, 1939, 930 Jewish refugees sailing from Hamburg, Germany on the SS St. Louis arrived in Mexico and were denied their visas. The ship then sailed to Cuba, and Razovsky, whose previous experience at NCJW included working in Cuba helping refugees, was one of the officials sent to help them. She reminisces in 1961, "When the offical word came through that the ship would have to leave with its passengers still on board, we were all thunderstruck and horrified. To this day it is painful to recall the grief and agony on that occasion. When the day and hour arrived for the ship to sail, we were all at the dock. Some of the American newspaper men were so broken by the news that they knelt and prayed and wept aloud; others cursed and raved; we ourselves were too crushed to do anything but weep." 12
National Refugee Service, 1939-1943
Overwhelmed with work, the National Coordinating Committee merged with two other organizations ( NCC Fund and the Greater New York Coordinating Committee ) to form the National Refugee Service (NRS) in June 1939. The NRS centralized and expanded refugee efforts, adding additional departments. Razovsky served as Director of the new Migration Department and later as Assistant to the Executive Director.
Razovsky was among the members of the Capital Loan Committee that began operating on October 16, 1939 to evaluate loan applications from refugees, who holding only visitor visas, were often barred from accepting employment. The funds were dispersed from an inherited NCC fund, the Rosenwald Capital Outlay Fund. Each loan was intended as a one time economic adjustment. Within two and a half months, the Loan Committee approved 24 individuals' applications spanning fifteen communities throughout the United States. Additional donations came from the American Joint Reconstruction Foundation, the Refugee Economic Corporation, outside communities and other sources. 13
In the Fall of 1938 in Evian-Les-Bains, France, President Franklin D. Roosevelt convened the Intergovernmental Committee on Political Refugees, whose purpose was to make a concerted effort to help German refugees. Out of all of the thirty-two nations there represented, United States included, only the representative from the Dominican Republic offered to accept large numbers of Jewish refugees. Rafael Leonidas Trujillo, Dominican Republic's Dictator who, between October 2-4, 1937, murdered 20,000 poor Haitian workers, all of them black, had motives aside from benevolence. His desire to make his Republic "white" was coupled with his need to improve his image with the United States. Trujillo hoped to settle 100,000 German and Austrian refugees on 24,000 acres of agricultural property, and the first six settlers arrived in Sosua in March 1940. Razovsky worked with James N. Rosenberg, President of the Dominican Republic Settlement Association (DORSA) to implement the plan, however, by 1942, due to the difficulties of wartime and refugee selection, there were only 472 settlers. 14
On September 5, 1940, the National Refugee Service received a telegram from passengers escaping Nazi Germany on S.S. Quanza, who had been denied entry into Mexico, despite the fact that thirty-five of them only wished to transfer to other ships bound for South and Central America. Razovsky writes, "The only creature on board the ship, who would have been permitted to land was a little Pekinese dog who carried a certificate of entry which the Mexican Government was prepared to honor." S.S. Quanza continued onward to Norfolk, Virginia, where it was scheduled to drop off coal before heading back to Lisbon. Razovsky, now NRS Assistant to the Executive Director; Evelyn Hersey, Executive Director of the American Committee for Christian Refugees; and several attorneys were among the party who met the ship at port. The attorneys served writs of libel on the ship, preventing the ship from sailing until a hearing could take place; and with pressure by various organizations and relatives, the State Department agreed to admit children under sixteen, persons with visas for Central or South America, and political refugees. After each case was heard by the Board of Special Inquiry, all eighty three refugees, sixty-six of whom were Jewish, were allowed temporary entry and were placed under the care of the National Refugee Service and the American Committee for Christian Refugees. 15
A few months before Pearl Harbor, the U.S. negotiated the seizure of Japanese, Austrians, Germans, and Italians in Panama with the Panamian Government. 16 Jewish refugees, escapees from Nazi terror, were among those arrested and sent to detention camps in Texas, Oklahoma, and Tennessee. A detainee writes, "I have been arrested in Panama in the open street by a common police man... without asking me who I am and of what nationality... Neither in Panama nor at any other country, where I lived, I had any kind of political activity or any connection with such matters..." 17 Razovsky appealed to the War and Justice Departments to ease conditions for the refugees in the camps and obtain their release. She writes, "... We were able to have the men at Stringtown [Oklahoma] transferred from Camp Blanding, Fla. where their situation was desperate because they had to be with the Nazis constantly and were mistreated. At Stringtown they have separate sleeping quarters although they are still obliged to eat with the Nazis..." 18 In February 1943 after State Department hearings, the Jewish detainees and their voluntarily detained relatives were transferred to Camp Algiers in New Orleans; by June approximately sixty were released on parole. 19
Razovsky, at that point, was handing in her resignation letter. After changes in NRS board leadership, Razovsky's responsibilities had been downgraded, and faced with a 30% cut in salary and the title of "Consultant," Razovsky resigned from the National Refugee Service on June 15, 1943. 20
United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Agency/American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee, 1944-1948
When the allied armies first breached Nazi lines in November 1942 liberating North Africa, plans for an international relief organization were in the works through the newly formed United Nations. While international committees were drafting the new agency's structure, President Franklin D. Roosevelt appointed New York Governor Herbert Lehman in charge of the Office of Foreign Relief and Rehabilitation Operations. In November 1943, 44 nations signed an agreement to establish the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Agency (UNRRA), with Lehman as its head. 21 Razovsky applied to "Governor Lehman's organization" in April 1943. 22 Having received no offers from UNRRA, Razovsky went on to work for the Common Council for American Unity, as Chief of Special Services and Editor of their publication "Interpreter Releases." The Common Council for American Unity's mission was to battle intolerance and discrimination towards foreigners living in the United States. She arranged to teach for UNRRA's Training Center in July 1944, and in September, UNRRA officially hired her to serve as a Displaced Persons Specialist for the European Missions Reserve. 23
By that time, the Allies had liberated France and U.S. troops had crossed over the defense system built by Hitler, called the Siegfried Line, and entered Germany. In April 1945, the Allies liberated the concentration camp of Buchenwald. Sargent Joseph Eaton, writes, "... The spriit of these men, incarcerated for years or even decades, remains even more striking in my memory. Some, many are wrecked physically and psychically, perhaps for life. But others are preserved, ready to live, ready to inspire those of us, who never had to love life as much as they had to in order to survive..." 24
The U.S. Army set up displaced persons camps as a first step in war relief, placing five to ten GI's in charge of thousands. Chaplain Aaron Kahan describes conditions as "pig stys where a thousand people live in a place unsuitable for one hundred. The food provided is of the same calibre..." 25
Willing to face these conditions, Razovsky arrived in London. It was common practice for UNRRA and private agencies to share employees when needed. Therefore, when the AJDC Paris office needed emergency staff, UNRRA officers loaned Razovsky to them. Loaning UNRRA staff to private agencies in France allowed UNRRA to have a presence where none was permitted; French authorities refused to allow UNRRA to manage displaced persons within French borders. 26
Razovsky worked for AJDC Paris from February 1945 until her return to the United States at the end of June. In Paris, she set up a Central Location Bureau for France, organized a Personal Service division for emergency relief, arranged the reunion of fifty displaced children with their relatives now in the United Kingdom, supervised casework for groups of displaced persons in various French camps, and arranged transit visas for children traveling through France to embarkation ports in Portugal and Spain. She was among the relief workers who accompanied the first contingent of children released from Buchenwald into temporary care in France and Switzerland. Many of these children emigrated to Palestine. 27
By May 1945, Razovsky was suffering from the effects of a poor diet and living conditions and appealed to her superiors to send her home. In July, she arrived in New York where she spent the next few months speaking on behalf of UNRRA at an UNRRA luncheon, a Providence Section, NCJW meeting, and for the Margaret McDonald radio show. Still feeling the ill effects of her overseas work, she went on leave from UNRRA for three months, eventually resigning from the agency on February 1946. By then, she had accepted a position with the AJDC as Director of Emigration for Germany and Austria.
Conditions in German DP camps remained deplorable and increasingly overcrowded, as Jews fleeing anti-Semitism in their native lands infiltrated the American zone. These Jews were not considered displaced by war under the classification made by UNRRA authorities, and care for them fell solely to Jewish organizations. According to Judge Simon H. Rifkind's (advisor to General Dwight D. Eisenhower ) report, issued in April 1945, there were approximately 100,000 Jews in all of the zones of Germany and Austria. Furthermore, negotiations with military authorities delayed AJDC workers from arriving in Germany and Austria until a month after VE-Day, in June 1945. Once established, the AJDC was able to supplement the DPs' basic needs provided by the UNRRA, shipping clothes, food, medical supplies, and religious and educational supplies. The 80 AJDC staff in Germany and Austria also served as a liaison between the Jews and the occasionally anti-Semitic U.S. Army, UNRRA, and local governments. American Jewish Year Book reporter Geraldine Rosenfield writes, "In this capacity the staff on numerous occasions served as trouble-shooters," thereby alleviating many difficult situations." 28